A Guide to the Papers of Henry Van Dyke, 1895-1925
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Henry Van Dyke 1895-1925
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7049, -a, -b, -c, -d
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
(7049) Purchase: Paul C. Richards, 1023 Beach Street, Brookline 46, Mass.; 1962 October 29.
(7049-a) Purchase: Goodspeed's Book Shop, 18 Beacon Street, Boston, Mass.; 1963 July 11.
(7049-b) Deposit: Clifton Waller Barrett, Charlottesville, Va.; 1963 December 17; made a gift 1991 July 1.
(7049-c) Deposit: Clifton Waller Barrett, Charlottesville, Va.; 1963 December 17; made a gift 1991 July 1.
(7049-d) Archival transfer, 1990 March 28.
Scope and Content
The papers contain a typescript on the poetry of Tennyson and a manuscript of an essay on Hamilton Mabie.
In thirteen letters to various correspondents Van Dyke discusses his writing projects, particularly "A leaf of spearmint," and "The song-sparrow"; his reaction to W.R. Nicoll's review of his A Gospel for the Age of Doubt; scholarly writing projects he directed, especially "Gateway series"; his views on world peace and on education, particularly entrance exams in English; royalties; and his schooldays, son's death, religious views, and personal life.
In a letter to Joseph LeRoy Harrison, Van Dyke regrets that he will be unable to write an introduction to Harrison's anthology [Fisherman's Verse?] due to work pressures and his inability to consult his collection of angling books.
There are also two photographs of Van Dyke.
Correspondents include the corresponding editor of The Youth's Companion, Richard Watson Gilder, Edward Leeds Gulick, Robert Underwood Johnson, J.T. Pike, F. L. Pleadwell, and Paul van Dyke.
Arrangement
Series I: Literary Manuscripts
Literary manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by title, or by the opening phrase if the title is not present.
Series II: Letters
Letters are filed in chronological order.
Series III: Photographs
Contents List
- Series I: Literary Manuscripts
  - Essay on Hamilton Mabie, beginning, "He is one of the..." 1900 February 24, AMsS, 2p. (Folder 1)
  - Criticism on the poetry of Tennyson, beginning, "In such poems as..." n.d., TMs, w/autograph corrections, 1p. (Folder 2)
- Series II: Letters
  - Henry Van Dyke to ____ Cary 1895 April 15, ALS, 2p. (Folder 3)
    Van Dyke discusses a minister's life; asks about an illustration for "A Leaf of Spearmint"; explains a photograph originally included with the letter and some poetry; also mentions the Century, the Alley (proper name?), St. Nicholas, an American sparrow, and an English sparrow.
  - Henry Van Dyke to Corresponding Editor of The Youth's Companion 1895 December 31, TLS, 1p. (Folder 4)
    Van Dyke declines to write a proposed article for The Youth's Companion because too busy.
  - Henry Van Dyke to Richard Watson Gilder 1897 January 12, ALS, 4p. (Folder 5)
    Van Dyke comments on a review of his book, The Gospel for an Age of Doubt, by W.R. Nicoll; says Nicoll's facts are wrong and he misread Van Dyke's book; also mentions: "Scotch Reviewer," British Weekly, The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire, Edward Gibbon, and Murray's standard edition of Gibbon.
  - H.V.D. to ____ 1900 April 9, ALS, 1p. (Folder 6)
    Van Dyke sends autograph to a man who asked for it in a letter. Letterhead is, "University Club, Cleveland."
  - H.V.D. to E.L. Gulick 1903 January 23, TLS, 2p. (Folder 7)
    Van Dyke reminds E.L. Gulick about the "Gateway Series" he is working on, particularly the teacher's volume; discusses royalty for books and entrance exams in English used by leading colleges; predicts such exams will be discarded as literature study develops.
  - H.V.D. to [Paul] Van Dyke 1903 March 24, ALS, 1p. (Folder 8)
    Van Dyke thanks his brother, [Paul] Van Dyke, for his letter of condolence re the death of H.V.D.'s son; mentions heaven and Christ; expresses thanks that there is still work to do.
  - H.V.D. to E.L. Gulick 1903 June 19, ALS, 1p. (Folder 9)
    Van Dyke thanks Gulick for showing him his prospectus of a survey of English literature; says he will submit it to the American Book Company; tells him he can work slowly on his mterial for teacher's volume in Gateway series. Note: letter was dictated. Written in unidentified hand. Signed by Van Dyke.
  - H.V.D. to J.T. Pike 1913 July 9, ALS, 3p. (Folder 10)
    Van Dyke reminisces on schooldays; says he would like to meet with boyhood friends, but expects sailing orders soon. Person and subjects mentioned: Livingston Street, Brooklyn; Master Davison; classroom discipline; "Thicks"; and "Cops."
  - H.V.D. to ____ Life 1913 July 27, ALS, 4p. (Folder 11)
    Van Dyke discusses possibility of universal peace; advocates a confederation peace versus a campaign against war; mentions functions of a diplomat; also mentions Boers and Balkans.
  - Henry van Dyke to J[oseph] L[e Roy] Harrison 1916 April 25, TLS. (Folder 12)
    Cannot write an introduction to Harrison's anthology (probably Fisherman's Verse, published in 1918).
  - H.V.D. to F.L. Pleadwell 1922 December 28, TLS, 1p. (Folder 13)
    Van Dyke gives references to publications containing some of his remarks on education. Person and subjects mentioned include: Mr. Edison, New York Times; New York American; Alonzo B. See; women's colleges; News and Observer of Raleigh, North Carolina; and North Carolina Teachers' Assembly.
  - H.V.D. to Robert U[nderwood] Johnson 1925 January 8, ALS, 2p. (Folder 14)
    Van Dyke mentions recovering from the grippe; expresses sympathy to Robert Underwood Johnson for his wife's death; encourages him to bear his loss and finish career valiantly and as a Christian.
  - H.V.D. to [Robert Underwood] Johnson n.d., ALS, 2p. (Folder 15)
    Van Dyke describes spring landscape; discusses changes to "The Song-Sparrow" (poem) which Johnson suggested; also discusses title for a prose sketch ("A Leaf of Spearmint") and lists several suggestions. Note: Autograph comments in an unknown hand written in pencil on page two.
  - H.V.D. to ____ n.d., ANS, 1p. (Folder 16)
    Van Dyke mentions Scribner's magazine and plate-proofs.
- Series III: Photographs
  - Book photogravure n.d.
    H.V.D., seated sideways.
  - Magazine photo n.d.
    H.V.D., profile.